Guide to the Allen Tanner Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Allen Tanner papers
1902-1986
GEN MSS 368
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.7
(5 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 1 portfolio
Papers include correspondence, photographs, writings and other materials by or relating to Allen Tanner, and particularly concerning his relationship with Pavel Tchelitchew. Correspondence consists of letters to Tanner, among them letters from René Crevel, Pavel Tchelitchew, Virgil Thomson, and Alexandra Zaoussailoff. Also included are several letters from Tanner to John Torson, and one letter from Lincoln Kirstein and one brief postcard from Edith Sitwell, both to Tchelitchew. Writings include holographs and typescripts by Tanner and unidentified writers, generally concerning Tchelitchew, as well as Tanner's life in the 1920's in New York and Paris. Among the photographs are pictures of Tanner and Tchelitchew. Additional materials includes printed items and other materials primarily concerning Tanner and Tchelitchew.
Tanner, Allen
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John A. Torson, 1987-1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials in the portfolio and in cold storage may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies and copy prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
ALLEN TANNER, 1898-1987
Allen Tanner was born on September 29, 1898. Early in life he showed signs of significant talent at the piano, and at age fifteen he went to Chicago, where he made his first appearance with an orchestra, followed by several concert tours in the West. He then moved to New York, where he worked as a concert accompanist for various vocalists, including Marguerite D'Alvarez. His talent in demand, Tanner performed often in New York and throughout the East.
In December of 1922, Tanner went to Berlin to pursue his musical career in Europe. Almost immediately he met the artist Pavel Tchelitchew, who was working as a set designer for the Russian Romantic Theatre. The two became friends, and this friendship soon grew into a relationship that would last over a decade. In early summer of 1923, they left Berlin for Paris, where they lived with Tchelitchew's sister, Alexandra Zaoussaïloff, for several years. In Paris, Tchelitchew worked on his painting while Tanner took work as a piano instructor. Tchelitchew's work soon caught the interest of Gertrude Stein, and for a time the two men were a part of Stein's circle of literary and artistic friends, a group which also included René Crevel and Virgil Thomson, both represented in this collection.
In the autumn of 1934, Tchelitchew and Tanner moved to New York. By this time, Tchelitchew was involved with the poet Charles Henri Ford, and when Tanner and Tchelitchew visited Tanner's home town of Chicago for an exhibition of Tchelitchew's work, Tanner stayed when Tchelitchew returned to New York. In the following decades, Tanner continued his musical career, living in New York during the 1950's and 1960's, and later in Belleville, Illinois, where he died on October 3, 1987.
Scope and Contents
The Allen Tanner Papers document the life of the pianist Allen Tanner, particularly his life in Paris in the 1920's with the artist Pavel Tchelitchew. The Papers have been arranged into four series; Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, and Additional Materials.
Series I, Correspondence, includes letters from René Crevel, Dame Myra Hess, and Virgil Thomson, and with several letters written by Tanner to John Torson. The majority of the correspondence consists of letters from Pavel Tchelitchew and from his sister, Alexandra Zaoussaïloff (nicknamed "Choura" throughout the collection), to Tanner (who is referred to as "Allousha" by both Tchelitchew and his sister). The letters from Tchelitchew date from 1928-1951, with the majority written after 1940, while Tchelitchew was living in New York. The letters discuss his life in New York, his work, the war in Europe, his travels to Arizona and Block Island, his sister Choura, and the lives of many of his friends, including Lincoln Kirstein, Edith Sitwell, Florine Stettheimer (in particular, her death), and Virgil Thomson. Included are several envelopes without corresponding letters, which have been placed with the letters according to the date of their postmark. The letters from Zaoussaïloff date from 1958-1972, after Tchelitchew's death in 1957. The letters concern her life in Paris, and her memories of Tchelitchew's life and his death. The letters also discuss the lives of many of her friends, including R. Kirk Askew, Jr. (Tchelitchew's dealer in New York), Lincoln Kirstein, Edith Sitwell, Gertrude Stein, Parker Tyler (particularly the writing of his biography of Tchelitchew, The Divine Comedy of Pavel Tchelitchew ), and various Russian friends and relatives, in particular her (and Tchelitchew's) half-sisters Mania and Varia Tchelitchew.
Series II, Writings, consists primarily of memoirs and recollections by Tanner of Tchelitchew and of his life in New York and Paris in the 1920's.
Series III, Photographs, contains photographs of Tanner, Tchelitchew, and friends and relatives, taken primarily in the 1920's. Also included are several photographs of the Diaghilev Ballet production of "Ode," designed by Tchelitchew, as well as several later photographs of Margaret C. Anderson, and two most likely of Tanner taken in the 1960's.
Series IV, Additional Materials, consists of printed items and other materials chiefly relating to Tanner and Tchelitchew.
Crevel, René, 1900-1935; Kirstein, Lincoln, 1907-1996; Sitwell, Edith, 1887-1964; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Tanner, Allen; Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989; Zaoussailoff, Alexandra
- Correspondence, 1922-1986; Series I; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - D'Alvarez, Marguerite, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Crevel, René, 1926-30, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Letters addressed to Tanner and Pavel Tchelitchew
      Includes: Postcard signed by Crevel, "Poupet," "Bébé" (e.g. Christian Bérard), "Tylia," and "Moma"
    - De Lamar, Alice, 1967 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dubal, David, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dungan, ----, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Draft of TLS from Tanner[?]
    - Hamill, Liz, 1986 Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hess, Myra, Dame, 1922, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, John F. Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Printed card
    - Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Ethel, 1964 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kochno, Boris, 1928 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Magallanes, Nick, 1968 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Malone, Robert J., 1986 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Morse, Harriet Klamroth, 1985 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Novaes (Pinto), Guiomar, 1962-66 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ranking, Patrice C., 1974 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Rothschild, Howard D., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      2 drafts of letters from Tanner
    - Scott, Zachary, 1963 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - State of New York Executive Chamber, 1966 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Stevens, Roger L., 1966 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1928-51 (Box 1, Folder 20-28)
    - Thomson, Virgil, 1970-83, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Torson, John, 1984-86 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Letters by Tanner
    - Turbyfill, Mark, 1967 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Tyler, Parker, 1960 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Wilhelm, Fred Wilhelm, Reta Jo, [1985] (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Yale University. Dept. of English, 1947 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Envelope only
    - Zaoussaïloff, Alexandra, 1957-72, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35-55)
    - ----, Paula and Tim (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified, [1985?] (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - THIRD-PARTY LETTERS
    - Kirstein, Lincoln to Pavel Tchelitchew, 19[44?] Sep 17 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Sitwell, Edith to Pavel Tchelitchew, 1928 Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Writings, 1963, n.d.; Series II; 0.2; (1 box)
  - WRITINGS OF ALLEN TANNER
    - "Corridor of Genius," 2 typescripts, both corrected, 1963 Sep 8 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "The Early Tchelitchew," typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Holograph about Tchelitchew and Charles Henri Ford, written on the back of an envelope (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "Tchelitschev's Parents," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "Tschelitscheff Superstitions," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "Visit to Belley - & Gertrude Stein," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - "Pavel Tchelitchew," typescript fragment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Untitled article about food, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Untitled typescript fragment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Photographs, 1902-1967; Series III; 0.4; (1 box)
  - TANNER, ALLEN
    - "Age 18"[?], [1926?] (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - As a child, [ca. 1902-06] (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
    - Head shot, [ca. 1920?] (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - In Guermantes (France), [1926?] (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - In Toulon (France), [ca. 1925?] (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - In Tunisia, [1926] (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - On boat to Tunisia, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - With Charles Vincent and Alexandra Zaoussaïloff, near Guermantes (France), 1933 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - With Pavel Tchelitchew, Paris, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - With Pavel Tchelitchew, Tunisia, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - With Alexandra Zaoussaïloff, Paris, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - With Alexandra Zaoussaïloff[?], unidentified woman, and unidentified man (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - [Tanner?] With neighbor (color print), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - [Tanner?] With unidentified woman, [ca. 1925?] (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - [Tanner?] With several unidentified women, [ca. 1920?] (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - TCHELITCHEW, PAVEL
    - Portraits and Snapshots
      - Age 5-6, Moscow, [ca. 1903-04] (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - In Tunisia, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 87-89)
      - Passport photo, ca. 1918-19 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - With Margaret Anderson, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - With Mabel Pace Tanner (Allen's mother), Guermantes (France), ca. 1931-32 (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - With Mabel Pace Tanner, Tunisia, [1926?] (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - "Ode," Diaghilev Ballet, Designed by Tchelitchew
      - Branitzka, L. L., "Tcherkas" and "Efimov", 1928 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      - Lifar, Serge, as "The Student", 1928 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      - Unidentified dancer, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - OTHER PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Anderson, Margaret C. and Lillian Siegel (color print), 1967 Aug 5 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Anderson, Margaret C. and Solita Solano, Orgeval (Yvelines, France) (color prints), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      Includes: Fragment of typescript letter by unidentified
    - Anderson, Margaret C. and "Fritz" (color print), 1967 Jan (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Chauviré, Yvette, 1948 Oct (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - "Douglas," "Josephine," and "Seton," Gallanach (Scotland), 1921 Jul (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Duncan, Isadora. Photo by Arnold Genthe (postcard), ca. 1920 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Gallanach House, Argyllshire (Scotland), 1921 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Gravesite of Serge Diaghilev, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - "Josephine," "Douglas," "Ruano[?]," and Gladys Waterbury, Gallanach (Scotland), 1921 Sep (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Karsavina, Tamara, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - "The Summer House," Mt. Harmony Road, Bernardsville, N.J., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Tanner, Florence[?] (Tanner's sister) as a child, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Tanner, "Grandma" and Martin Poole (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Tanner, Mabel Pace, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Tanner, Mabel Pace and Florence, Chateau LaGrange (Box 4, Folder 111)
      Includes: Typescript note by Tanner explaining the photo
    - Tchelitchew, Fyodor Sergeyevitch (Pavel's father), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Toumanova[?], Tamara, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Zaoussaïloff, Alexandra, Paris, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Zaoussaïloff, Alexandra[?], and unidentified man (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Unidentified building, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Unidentified house, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Unidentified woman, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Two unidentified women, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Unidentified woman on boat [to Tunisia?], [1926?] (Box 4, Folder 120)
- Additional Materials, 1923-1974; Series IV; 0.2; (1 box)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - "Allen Tanner, Pianiste," printed advertisement for lessons and concerts, [ca. 1923?] (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, printed program, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Blank card printed with picture of mother and child (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - "Exhibition of Paintings, Drawings, Caricatures, Autographs by Pavel Tchelitchew 1923-1932, from the Collection of Allen Tanner, Brentano's," printed program, 1964 Apr (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - "KWMU Magazine", 1974 Feb 1 (Box 5, Folder 125)
      Includes: photographs of Tchelitchew, 1923, and Jane Heap, n.d.
    - "Mme. Sarah Bernhardt (Herself)," printed program, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Newspaper clipping about a concert by Tanner, [ca. 1931-32] (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Newspaper clipping about stomach pain, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Newspaper clipping with program for a concert in hommage to Claude Debussy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - "Pavel Tchelitchew, 1898-1957, Rétrospective," Galerie Lucie Weill, printed announcement, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Postcard of Egyptian mummies, Musée Guimet (Paris, France), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - "The Spur," pp. 15-16, 1939 Apr (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - "What's in Your Name? Tanner," copy of printed article, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Card with address of Hugh Ford, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Cardboard box top with holograph list of musical works, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Envelopes, photograph sleeves and miscellaneous notes (Box 5, Folder 136)
      Most contain writing identifying various letters and photographs in the collection; apparently at some time in the past these were separated from their original contents
    - Genealogy of the Anderson and Tanner families, holograph (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Luggage identification card for Allen Tanner, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Typescript list of Tchelitchew's works owned by Tanner, to be sold by Brentano's, 1963 Sep (Box 5, Folder 139)
- Oversize
  (1 broadside)
  - Allen Tanner as a child (in Series III), [ca. 1902-06] (Box bsd, folder 146)
- Restricted Fragile
  (1 portfolio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 42 (Box port, Folder 140)
  - Box 2, folder 51 (Box port, Folder 141)
  - Box 2, folder 58 (Box port, Folder 142)
  - Box 5, folder 127 (Box port, Folder 143)
  - Box 5, folder 128 (Box port, Folder 144)
  - Box 5, folder 132 (Box port, Folder 145)
  - Box 4, folder 73 (Box cs, Folder 146)
  - Box 4, folder 75 (Box cs, Folder 147)
  - Box 4, folder 107 (Box cs, Folder 148)
  - Box 4, folder 117 (Box cs, Folder 149)
  - Box 4, folder 119 (Box cs, Folder 150)
  - Box 4, folder 120 (Box cs, Folder 151)